Guide to the Stephen F. Austin High School Scottish Brigade Drill Team and Alumni Association Records
University of Houston Libraries
Stephen F. Austin High School Scottish Brigade Drill Team and Alumni Association Records
1937-2011
1937-1978
2010-004
Stephen F. Austin High School Scottish Brigade
15.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes the records from the Scottish Brigade Alumnae association and the Scottish Brigade. The series included are: Scottish Brigade Alumnae Records; Scottish Brigade Alumnae Photographic and Video Material; Official Brigade Records; Scottish Brigade Performance Material; Scottish Brigade Photographic Material; Scottish Brigade Publicity Clippings; Stephen F. Austin Senior High School Yearbooks; and Scottish Brigade Memorabilia and Scrapbooks.
Historical Note:
The Stephen F. Austin High School Scottish Brigade drill team was founded by Beatrice Lytle in September of 1937. The Scottish Brigade’s mission was defined as service to school and community, as well as embracing the ideals of honor, spirit and loyalty. Drill teams played an important social role in the years that the Scottish Brigade was active. Girls’ sports teams were rare or nonexistent in many American high schools and colleges until the enforcement of Title IX in 1972, and drill teams like the Scottish Brigade offered a place to promote scholarship, discipline, respect, leadership skills, social skills and fitness to high school girls.
For the next forty years the Scottish Brigade performed at Austin High School football games, as well as drill team contests and city and state parades and festivals. The brigade disbanded on May 25, 1978. On the 50th anniversary of the founding of the Scottish Brigade, the alumnae decided to form an association to keep the memory and spirit of the Scottish Brigade alive. In 1987 the Scottish Brigade Alumnae Association formed and is still active providing scholarships to Austin High School students and planning yearly meetings of Brigade alumnae.
References:
Harwood, Nancy. “Scottish Brigade Alumnae members keep the spirit alive” The Leader. Houston, Texas [March 16, 2006].
“Scottish Brigade highlights” <<www.austin55.org/brigadehighlights.html>>. Accessed 5/12/2009 (created 12/5/00)
Bell, Richard C.“A history of women in sport prior to Title IX” The Sport Journal, Vol 10, No. 2 (2007). Accessed on May 19, 2011
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Stephen F. Austin High School (Houston, Tex.)
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Audiovisual materials; Correspondence; Financial records; Memorabilia; Photographs; Postcards; Rosters; Scrapbooks
Personal Name:
Lytle, Beatrice
Topical Term:
Marching drills
Custodial History:
The items were donated on behalf of the Scottish Brigade Alumnae Organization, and Nancy Grissom was the Vice Chair at the time of donation.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes the records from the Scottish Brigade Alumnae association and the Scottish Brigade. The series included are: Scottish Brigade Alumnae Records; Scottish Brigade Alumnae Photographic and Video Material; Official Brigade Records; Scottish Brigade Performance Material; Scottish Brigade Photographic Material; Scottish Brigade Publicity Clippings; Stephen F. Austin Senior High School Yearbooks; and Scottish Brigade Memorabilia and Scrapbooks.
The Alumnae records include the organizational documents, financial reports, plans for the luncheon and scholarship reports as well as photographs and photo albums of the Alumnae Association activities and luncheons.
The Scottish Brigade records include organizational documents, performance records and plans and photographs of Scottish Brigade members, performances and events. In addition it contains an extensive series of Scottish Brigade memorabilia.
Materials are arranged as Alumnae Records or Brigade records and then arranged by topic within each series. Whenever possible, dated materials are arranged chronologically. The collection is housed in 12 boxes and also includes two oversize items.
Detailed List of Contents
- Scottish Brigade Alumnae Records
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of 28 folders housed in 1 box and includes organizational documents, financial records, committee reports and other documents related to the founding and activities of the Scottish Brigade Alumnae Association. Of particular interest is the anthology book A Scottish Brigade Anthology which offers a concise and comprehensive history of the Scottish Brigade, its goals, members and founders.
  - Revised code of conduct, 1987-88 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Officer directories, 1989-2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board minutes, 1988-2010 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Luncheon agendas, 1990-2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Luncheon revenue statements, 2001-2010 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumnae luncheon minutes, 1990-2009 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alumnae Luncheon Salute to Betty Blakely performance script, 2-1-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scholarship Committee reports, 1991-2008 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Financial statements for Alumnae association, 1995-2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Business documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Alumnae Anthology, 1993-2008 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Alumnae Anthology edits to draft version, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - Alumnae Anthology rough draft, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - A Scottish Brigade Anthology, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 20th year reunion of the class of 1967 program, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Newsletters, 1988-2010 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Alumnae publicity newspaper clippings, press releases and articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Alumnae publicity newspaper clippings, press releases and articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Alumnae flyers, undated (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Trophy case donation to Austin High School, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annual luncheon volunteer sign-up sheets, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Tribute to Miss Beatrice Lytle, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Alumnae obituaries, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Scottish Brigade Alumnae Photographic and Video Material
  This series is comprised of 13 folders and 12 items housed in 3 boxes and includes the audiovisual and photographic records of the Scottish Brigade Alumnae association. Most of the items included relate to the Scottish Brigade luncheons although of particular interest are the three Scottish Brigade Performances videos which were created to be shown at the anniversary luncheons.
  - Luncheon negatives, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Luncheon negatives, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Luncheon negatives, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Luncheon negatives, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Luncheon negatives, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Luncheon negatives, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Luncheon negatives, 2002 & 2004 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Unidentified negatives, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Luncheon photo CDs 1 – 4, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Various unidentified brigade photos, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Luncheon photos, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - Slides from Brigadier reunions, luncheons and caroling, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Scottish Brigade - 50th Reunion memories video, undated (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Here Comes the Scottish Brigade video, undated (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Scottish Brigade Performances video, undated (Box 2, Item 3)
  - Scottish Brigade, revised Submaster A (1 of 2) video, undated (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Scottish Brigade, revised Submaster B (2 of 2) video, undated (Box 2, Item 5)
  - Black photo album – 22nd, 15th annual gathering of the clan, 2003 & 2010 (Box 2, Item 6)
  - Green photo album - 14th, 16th, 17th, 18th, 19th Annual gathering of the clan, undated (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Brown photo album - 6th, 7th, 8th, 12th Annual gathering of the clan, 1994-2000 (Box 2, Item 8)
  - Brown photo album – Visit to Miss Lytle, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th Annual gathering of the clan, Homecoming Luncheon, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Item 9)
  - Plaid photo album 50th reunion guest list and photos, 1987 (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Gold photo album - 50th Anniversary reunion, Organizational luncheon, 1st, 2nd and 3rd annual luncheons, Visit to Miss Lytle, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Red photo Album – 50th Anniversary reunion, Organizational luncheon, 1st and 2nd annual luncheon, Visit to Miss Lytle, 1987–1990 (Box 3, Item 3)
- Official Brigade Records
  This series is comprised of 9 folders housed in 1 box and includes the organizational documents of the Scottish Brigade, its financial documents, membership rosters and other administrative documents.
  - Founding documents (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Original constitution and bylaws of the Brigade and model constitutions, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 1, Item 1)
    - Revised constitution and bylaws, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1, Item 2)
    - Mission statement and inaugural member list, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 1, Item 3)
    - Membership selection chart, undated (Box 4, Folder 1, Item 4)
  - Financial Documents, 1940-1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Roster of Brigadiers, 1937-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1937–1940 and undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1941–1945 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1947, 1955, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Brigade Banquet programs, 1967 & 1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Stephen F. Austin Commencement program, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Installation procedures, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Scottish Brigade Performance Material
  This series is comprised of 37 folders and 4 items housed in 2 boxes and includes documents related to all aspects of the Scottish brigade’s performances. Marching plans, musical scores, song lyrics and marching handbooks are some of the more interesting documents in this series.
  - Musical scores, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Commands and Tactics, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Marching formations book, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Bagpipe maintenance manual, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Drill dances manual & Drill dances, 1962 & 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Programs, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Scripts of performances, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Scottish Dances of the Drill Corps binder, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - St Thomas games, 1940-1970 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Sam Houston games, 1939-1962 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - San Jacinto games, 1939-1964 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Spring Branch game, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Sterling games, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Waltrip games, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Westbury games, 1962-1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Wheatley games, 1967–1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Worthing game, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Yates games, 1967–1970 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Outside of district games, 1940–1965 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Summer performances, 1952–1969 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Shriner’s Ball performances, 1944–1965 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Opening day performances, 1949–1968 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Spring game performances, 1960–1971 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Formations plans, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Beamont games, 1939–1973 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Bellaire games, 1955–1967 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Davis games, 1944–1969 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Furr games, 1971–1973 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Galena Park games, 1947–1965 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Jones games, 1958–1971 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Lamar games, 1940–1956 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Lee games, 1970–1971 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Lincoln games, 1969–1973 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Madison games, 1966–1968 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Milby games, 1940–1973 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - North Shore games, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Reagan games, 1944-1969 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Performance binder, 1940–1950 (Box 5, Item 1)
  - Performance binder, 1950-1960 (Box 5, Item 2)
  - Performance binder, 1961-1970 (Box 5, Item 3)
  - Performance binder, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Item 4)
- Scottish Brigade Photographic Material
  This series is comprised of 7 folders and 3 items housed in 3 boxes. This series includes photo albums created by Scottish Brigade members, chronologically organized photos of Brigade members and Brigade events as well as a panoramic photo album containing photos of the entire Scottish Brigade for various years. Please note that Box 11 is an oversize box that contains items from several series and the panoramic photo album is an oversize item housed with the collection, but not in a box.
  - “The Colonels” photo album, 1938-1969 (Box 5, Item 5)
  - General photo album, undated (Box 5, Item 6)
  - Photos, 1930–1949 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Photos, 1950–1959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photos, 1960-1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Undated photos (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Brigade group photos, 1943–1950 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Panoramic photo album, undated (Item 1)
- Scottish Brigade Publicity Clippings
  This series is comprised of 9 folders housed in 3 boxes. This series includes newspaper clippings related to the performances and activities of the Scottish Brigade and its members as well as a run of the Austin Roundup, Stephen F. Austin High school newspaper from 1940-1978. Please note that Box 11 and Box 12 are oversize boxes, and Box 11 contains items from other series.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1930-1949 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1950–1959 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Powell River Digester (V 16, No 11) & New Frontiers (Vol II, No I), Nov 1940 & Fall/Winter 1960-61 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Austin Roundup, 1940–1945 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Austin Roundup, 1950-1953 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Austin Roundup, 1954-1960 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Austin Roundup, 1964-1978 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Various oversize clippings and newspaper pages, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Stephen F. Austin Senior High School Yearbooks
  This series is comprised of 5 folders housed in 1 box. This series includes newspaper clippings related to the performances and activities of the Scottish Brigade and its members as well as a run of the Austin Roundup, Stephen F. Austin High school newspaper from 1940-1978.
  - Yearbook, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Yearbook, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Yearbook, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Yearbook, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Yearbook, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Scottish Brigade Memorabilia and Scrapbooks
  This series is comprised of 7 folders and 25 items housed in 6 boxes with one loose item. This series includes costume items, props, marching flags, patches, scrapbooks and other memorabilia from the years that the Scottish Brigade was performing. Please note that Box 12 is an oversize box that contain items from other series and Item 2 is an oversize item housed with the collection, but not in a box.
  - Various “varsity” patches, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Sergeant Company A popsicle stick homemade writing book, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - The Scottish Tartans book, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Plaid material sample “The Stewart clan”, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Brigade ‘homecoming’ gift pouches, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Plaid uniform sash, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Wooden doll size bagpipe, undated (Box 7, Item 1)
  - Doll Scottish uniform, undated (Box 7, Item 2)
  - Brass placards: Name and awards, undated (Box 7, Item 3)
  - Black shoe, undated (Box 7, Item 4)
  - (2) Folding black and green uniform hat, undated (Box 7, Item 5)
  - Bagpipe jewelry pin, box of miscellaneous pins, metal bracelet, Scottish hat that is a jewelry box holding cuff links, undated (Box 7, Item 6)
  - Black beret, undated (Box 7, Item 7)
  - Cloth doll on stand, undated (Box 7, Item 8)
  - White spats and gold cord from uniform, undated (Box 7, Item 9)
  - Dual photo holder of unknown Brigadier and the letter ‘A’ with red ribbon, undated (Box 7, Item 10)
  - U.S. marching flag, undated (Box 7, Item 11)
  - Texas marching flag, undated (Box 7, Item 12)
  - Texas marching flag, undated (Box 7, Item 13)
  - Scottish Brigade marching flag, undated (Box 7, Item 14)
  - White marching flag with red “V” embossed, undated (Box 7, Item 15)
  - Highland Park Music Festival “Participant” plaque, undated (Box 7, Item 16)
  - Plaid bound scrapbook, undated (Box 8, Item 1)
  - Lt. Co. A Scrapbook, undated (Box 8, Item 2)
  - Paisley bound scrap book, undated (Box 8, Item 3)
  - Austin wooden scrapbook, undated (Box 8, Item 4)
  - Full size Scottish plaid kilt, undated (Box 9, Item 1)
  - Plaid kilt pouch, undated (Box 9, Item 2)
  - Stephen F. Austin Green Scottish brigade banner, wool, undated (Box 9, Item 3)
  - (2) Novelty swords, undated (Box 10, Item 1)
  - Brigade black bound scrapbook, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Posters, framed felt Scottish Brigade figure, display board, undated (Item 2)